RG 028:010, Commission to Effect Government Reorganization (Hull-Harper Commission), 1991-1992
Connecticut State Library
Commission to Effect Government Reorganization records
1991-1992
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Commission to Effect Government Reorganization
10.5 cubic feet
The Commission studied ways to reorganize state government into fewer cabinet level agencies and emphasized implementation rather than investigation.
RG028_010
Multiple
Historical Note
After the state realized only about $30 million from implementing recommendations of the Thomas Commission, the General Assembly created what was originally called the "Thomas Commission II." This new Commission was to study ways to reorganize state government into fewer cabinet level agencies. The legislature wanted the new Commission to have its committee chairmen as members to "have advocates and not detractors" when the results came in. It would also emphasize implementation rather than investigation so that it would provide a plan instead of a recommendation. The result was The Commission to Reorganize State Government, chaired by retired Connecticut Supreme Court Justice T. Clark Hull and State Senator Joseph Harper. It had eight members consisting of legislators, gubernatorial appoints and a member of the Connecticut State Employees Association.
One of the more controversial suggestions the Commission considered was eliminating the Comptroller's Office. Other recommendations included streamlining the state human services system by reducing the existing eleven agencies into four: the Department of Developmental and Rehabilitative Services, Department of Public Health and Addictive Services, Department of Children and Families, and the Department of Social Services. It also recommended appointment of a Commissioner of Higher Education/Board of Governors to oversee the current Department of Higher Education and establish a new Constituents Coordinating Council to identify and implement administrative saving in the system. The University of Connecticut and all its departments would maintain its current structure. A newly formed Connecticut State University and College System would consolidate all existing state colleges out side of UConn into four universities (Western, Eastern, Southern and Central) and five regional college campuses to administer the community, technical and two-year programs. The remainder of the report focused on recommended changes to improve service and state oversight of service provider networks, substance abuse, information technology, job creation and training, state agency finance, budget and purchasing practices. The Commission also studied the feasibility of merging the Departments of Environmental Protection and Agriculture and recommended against it. Finally, the Commission encouraged greater regionalization of state-wide services to promote standardization, adoption of total quality management principals in all state organizations, performance measures for state services, and personnel and merit reforms to allow greater flexibility and responsiveness.
Scope and Content
Includes meeting files for the full Commission as well as task forces, administrative files, and final report.
Related Material
RG 028:001, Commission to Investigate the Advisability of Consolidating Certain State Boards and Commissions and to Investigate the Public Health Laws, 1915.
RG 028:002, Commission on the Reorganization of State Departments, 1935-1937.
RG 028:003, Commission to study the Integration of the State Judicial System, 1943-1945.
RG 028:004, Commission on State Government Organization, 1949-1950.
RG 028:005, Commission on Services and Expenditures (Etherington Commission), 1971.
RG 028:006, Committee on the Structure of State Government (Filer Committee), 1976-1977.
RG 028:007, Human Servuces Reorganization Commission, 1977-1979.
RG 028:008, Governor's Study Group on Limitation of Expenditures, 1978.
RG 028:009, Commission to Study the Management of Stage Governerment, 1989-1991.
Index Terms
Persons:
Harper, Joseph; Hull, T. Clark
Organizations:
Connecticut. Commission to Effect Government Reorganization
Subjects:
Administrative agencies -- Connecticut; Connecticut. Connecticut. Commission to Effect Government Reorganization -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Executive departments -- Connecticut; State governments -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Minutes; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Records, 1991-1992
  - 1992-081
    - Full Commission meeting files
      - 1991 September-1992 February 7 (Box 1)
      - 1992 February 18-March 16 (Box 2)
    - Task force meeting files
      - Service Provider Network
        - 1991 October 21-1992 January 6 (Box 3)
        - 1992 January 9-February 6 (Box 4)
      - Human Services
        - 1991 October 21-December 4 (Box 5)
        - 1992 January 9-February 6 (Box 6)
      - Substance Abuse
        - 1991 October 22-December 17 (Box 7)
        - 1992 January 7-16 (Box 8)
      - Chief Information Officer
        - 1991 October 25-December 6 (Box 9)
        - 1991 December 20-1992 January 17 (Box 10)
      - SDE and Higher Education
        - 1991 October 21-December 19 (Box 11)
        - 1992 January 9-23 (Box 12)
      - Agency Budget and Finance
        - 1991 October 23-December 4 (Box 13)
        - 1991 December 9-1992 February 18 (Box 14)
      - Job Creation and Training
        - 1991 October 23-November 21 (Box 15)
        - 1991 December 5-1992 January 2 (Box 16)
      - Dept. of Environmental Protection / Agriculture
        - 1991 November 15-25 (Box 17)
        - 1991 December 23-1992 January 22 (Box 18)
      - Administrative files (Box 19)
        - Administrative file (Box 19)
        - Clippings file (Box 19)
        - Commission to Effect Government Reorganization biographies (Box 19)
        - Commission members addresses and phone numbers (Box 19)
        - Completed room reservation bulletin notices (Box 19)
        - Draft of final report, 3 folders (Box 19)
        - Final recommendations (Box 19)
      - Director's administrative files (Box 20)
        - Final report (Box 20)
        - Full Commission attendance sheet (Box 20)
        - Full Commission vote sheets (Box 20)
        - Full Commission vote sheet original (Box 20)
        - Letters sent with final report (Box 20)
        - Memos (Box 20)
        - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 20)
        - Commission to Reorganize State Government legislative authorization (Box 20)
        - Peter Goldfarb (Box 20)
        - Possible elimination of agencies (Box 20)
        - Task force attendance sheets (Box 20)
        - Task force assignments (Box 20)
        - Task force members names and addresses (Box 20)
        - Transmittal letters to State legislature (Box 20)
          - Human Services (Box 20)
          - Job Creation (Box 20)
          - Service Provider (Box 20)
          - Substance Abuse (Box 20)
        - Vote sheets (Chief Information Officer task force) (Box 20)
  - 2001-037
    - Meeting files, 1991 October 31-1992 April 7 (Box 1)
    - Recommendation of task force on Education and Higher Education (Box 1)
    - Final report, 1992 March (Box 1)